むった
(南波六太)＜一身上の都合で
自動車ﾒｰｶｰを退職し➡
After losing my job at a car maker for personal reasons,
新生活を
始めようとしていた 私の元に➡
I was trying to start a new life.
ジャクサ
送られてきたＪＡＸＡからの
通知｡➡
A letter from JAXA...
宇宙飛行士という大きな夢…➡
Do I still have a shot at fulfilling my dream
The New Astronaut Selection
Examination
果たして
今の私に叶えられるのか？＞
of becoming an astronaut?
Your application has been accepted.
(南波母)私が出したのよ！
I sent them your resume.
Space Brothers
Ah
This feels so good, different from usual
I have no idea what's going on
It feels so good
I never understand what's going on around me
Nothing makes sense to me
Full of questions
Feel so moon
I danced with you in a desert lit by the moon
I won't lose to the rabbit and fly high
I'll fly high
ひびと
(南波日々人)アッハハハ…➡
I could tell you about the UFO again,
またＵＦＯの話でも いいけど…｡
このエピソードの➡
but that wasn't the point of the story.
重要なポイントは
実は そこじゃないんですよ｡
#02  My Shining Star
Well, you've certainly made me curious.
まあ！それは興味深い｡
あの日…ＵＦＯを見た日➡
On the day I saw the UFO,
その場で兄と約束をしたんです｡
(女性記者)お兄さんと？ どんな!?
my older brother and I made a promise.
Your older brother? What was the promise?
｢一緒に
宇宙飛行士になろう！｣ってね｡
That we would become astronauts together.
お～ ロマンチックですね～｡
That's so romantic!
《ムッちゃん…
頑張ってるかな…》
Mu...
Are you working hard?
Hmm...
(吉原)ふ～ん…自動車メーカーに
居た人か～｡スゴイね～｡➡
You used to work for a car maker?
That's impressive...
うちは歓迎だけど｡
あ…ありがとうございます｡
You're certainly welcome here.
Th-Thank you very much.
《日々人…お前の気持ちは
正直 スゲ～嬉しかったけど➡
Hibito,
I was happy to know how you felt.
あにき
このままいくと 兄貴の俺が
お前に引っ張られることになる…》
But at this rate, the little brother will lead the older one.
《はぁ…これで いいんだよな…》
It's better this way...
シャロンおばちゃ～ん
こんばんは！➡
Good evening, Aunt Sharon!
田村の ね～ちゃんも！
And Ms. Tamura!
(田村)こんばんは！
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)いらっしゃい 六太｡➡
Good evening.
Welcome, Mutta.
今日は１人？
うん！日々人は
まだ 家で勉強だよ｡
Are you alone today?
Yeah, Hibito's still studying at home.
月 見えた？
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)ええ 今日は田村さんが
合わせてくれたわ｡
Did you see the moon?
Yes.
Tamura helped me line everything up.
へぇ～…へっ…｡
へっ…へっ…｡
ハァ～…ハ～｡
おおぉ～～!!まっぶし～!!
Wow!
It's so bright!
Awesome!
スゲ～ッ!!
わっ…わっ わ～っ!!
現在
ウッフフ…｡
(CD:声)もっかい いくぞ 日々人！
≪シャロンおばちゃ～ん≫
Let's try it again, Hibito!
Aunt Sharon!
(CD:六太･日々人の声)せ～の！
Ready and...
Aunt Sharon?
おばちゃ～ん 来たよ～！
I'm here!
久しぶりだなぁ…シャロン望遠鏡｡
It's been forever since I used the Sharon Telescope.
Wow!
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)あなたが来るっていうから
合わせといたのよ｡
I heard you were coming, so I lined it up.
おばちゃん…｡
Aunt Sharon.
Welcome, Mutta. Are you alone today?
いらっしゃい 六太｡
今日は１人？
Yeah, Hibito's training at NASA.
ナサ
日々人はＮＡＳＡで訓練中だよ｡
おっ なんか懐かしい曲が…｡
Oh! This song sounds familiar.
六太と日々人の
子供の時の演奏よ これ｡
This is a tape of you performing with Hibito.
(CD:声)アッハハハ…｡
Hibito, why are you laughing?
(CD:声)日々人 何 笑ってんだよ！
(CD:声)アッハハハ…｡
(CD:声)だって ムッちゃんの顔が
面白いんだもん｡
'Cause your face looked all funny!
かあ
うちの母ちゃんがね 俺に内緒で
ＪＡＸＡに履歴書 送ったんだ｡➡
My mom
sent JAXA my resume without telling me.
日々人に言われた
みたいなんだけど…｡
I guess Hibito asked her to do it.
書類選考 通ったの
1225人中ね…315人だって｡
Out of 1,225 applicants, 315 were accepted.
Then you did well to pass.
凄いじゃない｡それに通るなんて｡
Nah, I didn't do anything.
いや…俺は
何もしてないんだけどね｡
六太の実力なら通るって
わかってたのね 日々人は…｡
Hibito must have known you were qualified.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)じゃあ 次は一次審査か…
難しい筆記試験ね｡
Next up is the first exam,
a very difficult written test.
受けないんだよ…｡
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)どうして？
I won't take it.
Why not?
こう…サラサラ～っとね➡
A tiny shake,
ふるい落とされるって…残りの
315人中から２人か３人だよ➡
and it all falls off.
Only two or three of the remaining three hundred and fifteen
宇宙飛行士に
なれんのって…無理だよ｡
can become astronauts.
It's impossible.
Want to play some music?
久しぶりに ｾｯｼｮﾝしてみよっか？
え～ もう忘れちゃったよ｡
I've already forgotten how...
Huh?
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)ねえ 六太…｡
Say, Mutta...
ここにトランペットがあります｡➡
I have a trumpet here.
ピアノもあります｡➡
I also have a piano.
As well as a guitar and drum.
ギターも太鼓も
ハーモニカもあります｡➡
I even have a harmonica.
どれを やってみたい？
Which would you like to play?
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)((え～!? 全部やるの？))
All of them!
Oh? You're going to play all of them?
Well, I can't decide until I've tried them all.
((だって 全部やってみなけりゃ
決められない))
昔 六太に そう聞いたら
｢全部！｣って言って➡
Remember when I asked the same question when you were little?
片っ端から 音を鳴らしていったの
覚えている？…１時間かけて｡➡
And you tried out every single instrument?
For a whole hour.
You ended up choosing the trumpet.
それであなた その中で
トランペットを選んだのよ｡➡
｢どうして？｣って聞いたら…｡
When I asked you why...
((この中で一番 音が出にくい！))
Because it's the hardest to play.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)昔の あなたって
そんな子だったのよ｡
That's how you used to be.
何にでも どんどん挑戦して
難しいことを選んだ｡
You were always tackling the biggest challenges you could find.
そうだったかな～｡
トランペットを選んだのは➡
Are you sure about that?
I have a feeling I chose the trumpet because it was shiny.
単に一番
金ピカだったからじゃないかな～｡
That's fine, too.
それなら それでいいのよ｡➡
今のあなたにとって
一番 金ピカなことは な～に？
Right now, what do you consider to be your shining star?
今の俺にとって…？
Right now?
Now, try playing the trumpet.
さあ トランペットを持って
音を出して｡
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)上手くなくてもいいし
間違ってもいいのよ 六太｡
It's fine if it doesn't sound good.
No one will blame you for making a mistake, Mutta.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)まずは 音を出して｡
You need to try making noise first.
You have to make noise before you can make music.
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)音 出さなきゃ
音楽は始まらないのよ｡
始まらない…｡
Before I can make music...
《俺にとって 金ピカな事…》
My shining star...
(田村)え～｡今日 六太さん
来てたんですか？
What? Mutta was here?
Yep.
ＪＡＸＡの一次審査
受けるかどうか 迷ってたみたい｡
He wasn't sure if he wanted to take the initial JAXA exam.
(田村)そうなんですか？
六太さんは悩んだ時とか➡
Really?
Mutta always comes by
いつも１人で
ここに来てましたもんね｡➡
when he has something on his mind.
Hibito never had that problem.
日々人さんは まったく
そんな事なかったけど…｡
六太は何でも出来る
｢凄い兄貴｣になりたかったのよ｡➡
Mutta wanted to become an amazing older brother who could do everything.
いつの間にか…
日々人の前で失敗することを➡
So he became scared of doing anything wrong in front of Hibito.
すごく恥じるように
なっちゃったけど…｡
それで 六太さんは帰る時
どんな顔をしてました？
How did Mutta look when he left?
(吉原)こんにちは～！➡
Hello!
We're from Yoshiwara Repair, offering automotive repair at a low price.
なんでも格安修理屋の
｢シューリー吉原｣で～す｡
(客)これなんだけど～｡
(吉原)あ～かなり古い型ですね…｡
Here it is.
Ah, it appears to be an older model...
きみ
新人君… 君 できるコレ？
Newbie, can you handle this?
フッ…余裕です！
Heh.
Piece of cake!
おっ…おお～っ!!
All done.
できた！
(吉原)は…早い！
(客)ありがとうございます｡
F-Fast!
Thank you very much!
いえいえ 早さがウチの売りです｡
Not at all. We pride ourselves on our speed!
ま…今は こんなもんだ｡
Well, this is all I can do right now.
今はね…｡
At least for now.
うわっ…痛っ！
((おばちゃん 俺さ～…➡
Aunt Sharon.
You know...
行くとか
日々人には 火星
言っちゃったけど➡
I told Hibito that I would go to Mars,
やっぱり まずは
月に行きたいんだよね～｡➡
but I'd like to go to the moon first...
だって 月に望遠鏡を立てたら
ここからより➡
You said that if we put a telescope on the moon, we could see farther into space, right?
はる
遙かに 壮大な宇宙が見える
って言ってたよね！))
((うん 言ったね))
I did.
((月に行くために
宇宙飛行士になるよ｡➡
I'll become an astronaut, so I can go to the moon.
英語は おばちゃんに
教わってるから あとは➡
You've been teaching me English,
so I just need to major in the sciences and get a doctorate.
はくしごう
自然科学系の大学を出て 博士号を
取ったりすれば いいらしいんだ))
(ｼｬﾛﾝ)((そこまで調べたの？➡
You've already done your research.
Sounds like you're serious about this.
何だか 急に
やる気になったわね))
((これだけは
日々人に負けたくないからね))
I can't let Hibito beat me there.
I will reach the moon before Hibito.
((日々人より 先に月に行って
｢シャロン望遠鏡｣をたてるよ))
And I'll build the Sharon Telescope!
((わかった｡楽しみにしてる))
I understand.
I can't wait to see it happen.
I spent so much time pretending to forget my dream,
＜忘れたふりを
続けていたせいか➡
本当に自分の
大事な気持ちを忘れていた＞
I actually did forget it.
《シャロンと話して よかった…
シャロンおばちゃん 俺は…》
I'm glad I was able to speak with Sharon.
Aunt Sharon, I...
《俺は…
宇宙へ行きたい…》
I...
want to go to space!
＜書類選考を
通ってから１ヶ月｡➡
A month after my application was accepted,
First Exam Hall
あっという間に
筆記試験の日が来た…＞
it was time for the first exam.
Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency
＜受験者は300人以上｡
この中から➡
Over three hundred would take the exam.
Only two or three would become astronauts...
宇宙飛行士に選ばれるのは
ほんの２～３人＞
《ハハハ…子供の時から
シャロンおばちゃんの元で➡
I'd learned English from Aunt Sharon when I was a kid.
英語を学んだ私に
これしきの英語問題など！》
They can't stump me...
《宇宙開発の｢う｣の字もない!!》
None of these words have to do with space!
《一般常識問題ばかりで来るか
ＪＡＸＡ!?》
JAXA's testing us on ordinary vocabulary?!
《完全にヤマを外した～っ!!》
I gambled completely wrong.
も…もちろんです｡
Are you ready?
O-Of course.
チクッとしますよ｡
This will sting.
チクッ｡
はうっ…｡
Sting.
上…下…➡
Up.
Down.
え～っと…こっち｡
Uh... This way.
こっちって どっちですか？
右です 恐らく｡
Which way is this way?
Right, I think.
恐らくとか やめて下さい｡
Don't guess.
First Exam Hall
Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency
二次試験に進めますように！
Please let me make it to the second exam!
《私は宇宙へ行きたい》
I want to go to space.
《その一心だけで
試験に臨んだわけだが…》
That's all that's driving me now.
Weeks Later
[TV]出た！牛肉72.5％使用!!➡
Here it is! 72.5% beef...
新発売 ボンカリー！
The new Bon Curry.
[TV](ﾗﾓｽ)マサオもガンバレよ！
[TV](ﾏｻｵ)うん！
Keep at it, Masao.
た～いま｡
(母)おけ～りぃ｡
I'm home.
Welcome home!
今晩 何？
ボンカリー｡
What's for dinner?
Bon Curry.
うわ～ ミスった！
昼もカレーだったよ…｡
Eesh, I screwed up!
I had curry for lunch.
大丈夫｡
｢ボンカリーうどん｣だから｡➡
Don't worry... It's Bon Curry Udon.
あ そうだ ムッちゃん｡➡
Oh, that's right, Mu.
ＪＡＸＡから何か来てたよ｡
合格通知？
There's something from JAXA for you.
Maybe you passed?
うわ！っとっとっと…｡
Mom!
母ちゃん！まず それ言えよ！
ボンカリーより!!
You should've mentioned that before talking about the Bon Curry!
Well?
どうだった？
Oh!
あらら…｡
Hey! Where are you going, Mutta?
ちょっと！どこ行くの？六太!?
ついでに 牛乳買ってきて！
低脂肪～!!
Buy some milk on your way back!
Skim!
《すげぇ…すげぇ…➡
Wow.
Wow...
スゲェ～ッ!!》
Wow!
ハァ ハァ ハァ…｡
待って～イタッ!!
Wait for me!
≪エ～ン…待って…≫
Don't cry.
Hey, stop crying!
Oh, I have to buy a cake!
わぁ！ケーキ買ってこなきゃ｡
何の曲？
さあ？
What song is that?
Beats me.
Get up! Come on!
Pull it together.
Let's go!
I play a tune with no melody,
《メロディなきメロディを奏で➡
and walk where there is no road.
道なき道へ行こう》
This will take me
《そこに 俺にとって一番の➡
to my shining star!
金ピカがあるのだ！》
Yeah, it's fine...
ああ 大丈夫だって｡
ちゃんと着いたよ ＪＡＸＡに！
I made it to JAXA!
今 トイレだから｡
Well, I'm currently in the restroom.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](母)もうすぐ二次試験ね｡➡
The second exam is coming up!
Are you nervous? Well? Are you nervous?
キンチョーしてる？
ねぇねぇ キンチョーしてる？
Of course I am... Stop teasing me, Mom!
当たり前だろ！冷やかしは
やめてくれ 母ちゃん!!
I'll teach you the secret for calming your nerves.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](母)緊張をほぐす必殺技
教えてあげよっか？
I'm just fine...
もももういいから！
ありがとう 母ちゃん｡
Thanks, Mom.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](母)
手のひらに｢人｣っていう字を
百回くらい書くとね…｡
You write the character for person on your palm a hundred times.
[ｹｲﾀｲ](母)
手が くすぐったい アハハ…｡
That tickles your hand and...
ああっ！か 母ちゃん!!
M-Mom!
No, I've gotta think positive right now.
《いや…こんな時こそ
ポジティブに考えよう…》
《もう 失うものは何もない!!》
I have nothing left to lose!
＜私を含めて 今残っている
受験者は４５人＞
Including myself, there are forty-five remaining candidates.
＜これから始まる二次審査では➡
New
Astronaut
Selection
Waiting Room
The second exam will reduce that number to eight.
そこから８人に
絞られちゃうのだ＞
New Astronaut Selection
Waiting Room
(係員)１１番 南波さん
面接室へどうぞ｡
Number 11, Nanba. Please come to the interview room.
は ハイ!!
Y-Yes, sir!
じゅ…受験番号Ｂ－１１番
南波六太です｡
I-I'm number B-11, Nanba Mutta!
I-It's a pleasure to be here.
よ よろしくお願いします｡
(面接官)はい よろしく｡
Right, a pleasure.
《こ…怖ぇ～!!》
S-Scary...
Oh, is it possible that...
(面接官)あれ？もしかして…｡
はい！
Yes?
(面接官)南波日々人飛行士の
ご親戚か何かですか？
Could you be a relative of astronaut Nanba Hibito?
は…はい！
日々人は私の弟です｡
Y-Yes! Hibito is my little brother.
ああ そうなんだ｡
Oh, really?
A-Actually, I taught him everything he knows.
実は 弟を あそこまで育てたのは
私と言っても過言ではないと…｡
《ここは
日々人の背に乗っておこう》
Time to ride his coattails.
(田沼)フンッ…｡
(面接官)え～では いくつか
質問をします｡
Then we have a few questions for you.
≪あ ありがとうございました！
それでは 失礼します≫
New Astronaut
Selection
Interview Room
Th-Thank you very much!
Goodbye, then.
《なんてこった…
悪いクセが出てしまった…》
I can't believe it...
I let my bad habit take over.
《変な奴だと思われてしまったら
どうしよう》
What if they think I'm weird?
《面接中 ある小さな雑念が
私を捕らえ 邪魔し続けた》
There was a
tiny irritant that bugged me throughout the entire interview.
It kept me from focusing on the interview at all.
《そのせいで私は 全っ然 面接に
集中できなかった気がする》
The screw on the chair was loose!
《イスのネジが
ゆるゆるだったのだ！》
《ありえね～よ…
ＪＡＸＡだぞ ここ…》
I can't believe it...
This is JAXA!
《日本の宇宙開発の
最先端にありながら➡
A chair with a loose screw
in an office on the front line of the Japanese space program!
イスのネジが ゆるいなんて…》
《私は ずっと
変な姿勢だったと思う》
My posture was definitely odd.
《締めたい…》
Must tighten!
They'll probably reject me right off the bat, due to my posture.
《変な姿勢だった私は まず最初に
不合格にされるだろう…》
《人生なんて ネジ１個で
狂っちまうんだなぁ》
A single screw
can throw a wrench into your life...
《日々人…》
Hibito...
あなたも受験生ですよね？
You must be one of the applicants.
Huh?
(ケンジ)見たところ同学年かな？
３１くらいですか？
You look like you're around the same age as me.
Thirty-one-ish?
いかにも…３０と１歳ですが｡
Yep... sure am.
I'm thirty and one years old.
うっし！当たった!!
Yes!
I guessed right!
Huh?
(ケンジ)同じく３１で受験生の
真壁ケンジです｡
I'm Makabe Kenji. A 31-year-old applicant like yourself.
これから１週間
がんばっていきましょう！
Let's do our best over the upcoming week.
《おお～っ!!》
南波六太です！
よろしく！
I'm Nanba Mutta...
A pleasure.
《レトロな髪型の割に
なんて爽やかな青年だ！》
His hair is old-fashioned, but he carries himself quite well.
《この歳で 同い年のことを
同学年なんて言うあたり➡
He still calls people his age "classmates."
And he still sounds young at heart...
まだまだ青春してやがるな》
いい髪形してますね｡
I like your hair.
アハハハハ！南波さんの
ヘアスタイルも素敵ですね｡
Your hair is also wonderful, Nanba.
It only took us ten minutes to break the ice.
＜我々は１０分で打ち解けた＞
えっ!?マジでお兄さんなの？
あの南波日々人の｡
You really are Nanba Hibito's older brother?
そう｡似てないけどね｡
Yeah. Not much resemblance, though.
＜彼 真壁ケンジ君とは
仲良くやっていけそうだ＞
I have a feeling that I'll get along just fine with Makabe Kenji.
Mu, would you like some tea?
くん
ムッ君 お茶飲む？
サンキュー ケンジ｡
Thank you, Kenji.
あの女子も受験生かな？ムッ君｡
Is that woman an applicant, as well, Mu?
見たところ…２６｡
She looks to be around twenty-six.
Yeah.
《なんてこった…!!》
I don't believe it...
That beautiful woman wants to become an astronaut?
《あんなキレイな人も
宇宙飛行士を目指してんの？》
ほしか
(面接官)どうしました？星加さん｡
What's the matter, Hoshika?
(星加)ん？ええ ちょっと…
遊び半分で➡
Oh, right...
I fiddled with the chair to make the exam more interesting.
イスに少し細工しといたんです｡
細工？
The chair?
このイス わざと片側のネジを
ゆるめてあるんです｡
I deliberately loosened one of the screws on the chair.
Deliberately? Why?
(面接官)わざと？どうして…｡
座ってみると
若干ガタつくんですよ｡
When you sit, it's possible to tell something's wrong.
この小さな違和感に気づく
受験者はいるかなと思いまして｡
I was wondering how many applicants would actually notice.
ほ～う｡
そんなの気づく受験者なんて
いるんですかね？
Oh, did any notice?
Ａ班の時はゼロでしたけどね➡
None of the candidates from group A did.
今回のＢ班には
３人もいました｡➡
But in group B,
there were three who did.
１人目は すぐネジに
気づきましたが➡
The first noticed the loose screw,
その後 別に
気にも留めない様子でした｡➡
but he didn't seem particularly concerned.
２人目は気づいた時
思わず笑ってしまい➡
The second started laughing when she noticed,
and seemed surprised to realize she was laughing.
笑った自分に驚いてました｡
そして もう１人は…｡
As for the third...
He spent the entire interview, arm extended, attempting to tighten the screw.
ず～っとネジを締めようと
必死に手を伸ばしていました｡➡
実際 ちょっと締まってました｡
He actually managed to screw it in some.
それって 単に面接に
集中できない人達なんじゃ…｡
Doesn't that mean they had difficulty focusing on the interview?
(星加)ははは…まあ
そうとも取れますね｡➡
Well, that's one way to see it.
That's why I was just fooling around.
だから 遊び半分ですよ｡➡
だけど 僕が初めて
ここで面接を受けた時➡
But when I came here for my first interview,
同じことをされたんです｡
the same thing was done to me.
毛利さんに｡
By Mohri.
《こ この人…》
Th-This woman...
ごちそうさま｡
Thank you.
《１人なのに ちゃんと
｢ごちそうさま｣を言ってる…》
...said thank you when no one else was around.
《なんて幸せそうに
お昼を食す人だ…》
She looked so happy when she was eating her lunch.
賭けてみますか？
Interested in a wager
その３人が…➡
on whether those three
残るかどうか…｡
will make the cut?
The stars I admired were too bright for me
so I quietly closed my eyes
I have faith in you, as you stand alone, full of doubts
I'm right here, next to you
Come now, take my hand and hold it tight
If you do, we will always
have hope, shine with light
and overcome whatever we might face
Do you see how wonderful this world is
and how our future unfolds?
Even the tears we shed and could not put into words
will one day dry up, I am sure
One by one the smiles spread
and ascend towards the starlit sky
＜宇宙飛行士を目指す者は
パンツも脱がなければならない➡
#03 The Man with the Advantage
and the Running Female Doctor
Next time, on
Space Brothers
Why do I have to remove my underwear to become an astronaut?
…なんて知ってた？ケンジ＞
(ケンジ)＜まあ 想定内＞
Were you expecting this, Kenji?
Well, I'm not surprised.
＜厳しい審査が進む中
私は気づく＞
As I struggle through the grueling exam, I notice that
＜みんな 私が弟から審査内容を
聞いてて 有利だと思ってるんだ＞
everyone believes my brother gives me an advantage.
＜しまった！その手があったか＞
Damn! I should have played that card...
＜みんなに勝つためには 全部
１番になるぐらいじゃないと➡
If I'm going to make it, I'll have to win in every category.
…と思う私の前に
立ちはだかったのは➡
But Itou Serika is standing in my way!
いとう
あの伊東せりかさんであった＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
The Man with the Advantage and the Running Female Doctor.
＜走る女性って いいよね＞
I like watching a woman run...
パンパカパーン！
This Week's Space Photo
This week's space photo!
今週の宇宙写真です！
スッゲー！
Awesome!